<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Django | Herberth's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://herberthamaral.github.io/blog/categories/django/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://herberthamaral.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T18:07:18-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://herberthamaral.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Herberth Amaral]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Commands Conversion Table From MySQL to PostgreSQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://herberthamaral.github.io/blog/2013/02/22/one-who-has-no-dog-hunts-with-a-cat-a-sed-story/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-22T12:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://herberthamaral.github.io/blog/2013/02/22/one-who-has-no-dog-hunts-with-a-cat-a-sed-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The above title (One who has no dog hunts with a cat - &ldquo;Quem não tem cão caça com gato&rdquo;) is a portuguese proverb which
exemplifies the developer routine regarding to adapting tools and creating others when there are no other available.</p>

<p>Those who use an IDE (like Visual Studio) and a static-typed language are quite used to use the &ldquo;refact&rdquo; tool. It allows
you to rename variables and methods, extract methods, rename classes and more, without breaking the code. There are even
other extensions, like resharper, which make it even more powerful.</p>

<p>Non-static-language programmers, like me, are often jealous of what C# guys can do without too much effort.  Because of
the nature of dynamic languages, is very hard to develop a tool to do exactly what Visual Studio can do. We have to find
our way to fix our code in multiple places. And we often do it the hard way.</p>

<p>Sometime ago I read a serie of posts called <a href="http://blog.sanctum.geek.nz/series/unix-as-ide/">&ldquo;Unix as an IDE&rdquo;</a> and it taught me how to use my enviroment to edit code more efficiently.</p>

<p>One of the things the series of posts havent showed me is the power of <strong>sed</strong>. This simple tool can do almost the same
thing as Visual Studio&rsquo;s refact tool does sometimes.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s suppose we are maintaining an old PHP project that has queries all over the place and which those uses
&ldquo;mysql_db_query&rdquo; (now deprecated) instead of &ldquo;mysql_query&rdquo;. Here&rsquo;s a life-saving command:</p>

<pre><code>$ find /your/project/folder/ -name "*.php" | xargs sed -i s/mysql_db_query/mysql_query/
</code></pre>

<p>We can read it as follows: &ldquo;find every file ending with *.php in folder /your/project/folder and then substitute
mysql_db_query with mysql_query in each one of them&rdquo;. Pretty simple, huh?</p>

<h3>A more complicated example</h3>


<p>I&rsquo;m working on a Django project which uses <a href="https://github.com/tzangms/django-bootstrap-form">bootstrapform</a>
to better rendering some forms. However, since we&rsquo;re moving to <a
href="http://django-crispy-forms.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">Crispy Forms</a>, bootstrapform is no longer needed. So
let&rsquo;s remove it!</p>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s change <pre> %}</pre>  to <pre> %}</pre> inside templates. We
can do it as follows:</p>

<pre><code>$ sed --in-place 's/ {% load bootstrap  %}/{% load crispy_forms_tags  %}/' `find . -name "*.html"`
</code></pre>

<p>The command is slightly different from the previous one, but it works like a charm.</p>

<p>The second one is a bit more difficult. We need to change</p>

<pre>{{any_form|bootstrap }}</pre>


<p></p>

<p>to</p>

<pre>{% crispy any_form %}</pre>


<p></p>

<p>There are no other way: you need to have some regex knowledge to pick this up:</p>

<pre><code>$ sed --in-place 's//{% crispy \1  %}/' `find . -name "*.html"`
</code></pre>

<p>In this case, <a href="http://www.regular-expressions.info/brackets.html">grouping</a> saved my day. It is important to
remember that sed does not only work on source code files: it works everywhere.</p>

<p>If you are a programmer that uses Unix, keep your sed skills sharp. If you uses windows to work, I can recommend <a
href="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/packages/sed.htm">sed for windows</a> or cygwin for a more complete environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Template for Django Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://herberthamaral.github.io/blog/2013/02/04/a-new-template-for-django-projects/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T13:00:00-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://herberthamaral.github.io/blog/2013/02/04/a-new-template-for-django-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since Django 1.4 it is possible to use project templates. This means that you can start off your Django project
with a different project structure, which also means that you can avoid some initial configuration hassle.</p>

<p>Django follows Python&rsquo;s principle of &ldquo;explicit is better than implicit&rdquo;. And this is the justification I&rsquo;ve got when I
asked why Django does not have some configurations done by default. I think &ldquo;convention over configuration&rdquo; is not
necessarily &ldquo;explicit is better than implicit&rdquo;&rsquo;s enemy. Both can live together as long you keep the configurations
explicit.</p>

<p>Thinking about that I&rsquo;ve decided to write a project template which eliminates some of the Django&rsquo;s annoyances when
starting a project, mainly related to paths (templates, media and static). This is specially useful for newcomers so
they don&rsquo;t lose a lot of time configuring the project.</p>

<h3>Show me it working!</h3>

<p>You can start off a project using this template like this:</p>

<pre>
$ django-admin.py startproject myproject \
  --template=https://github.com/herberthamaral/django_project_template/archive/master.zip
$ cd myproject
$ python manage.py runserver
</pre>


<p>At this point you can point out your browser to <code><a href="http://localhost:8000">http://localhost:8000</a></code> and you can see Django&rsquo;s initial
page. But, if you point it to <code><a href="http://localhost:8000/static/readme.txt">http://localhost:8000/static/readme.txt</a></code>, you can also see the static folder&rsquo;s
configuration working. The same for the media folder: <code><a href="http://localhost:8000/media/readme.txt">http://localhost:8000/media/readme.txt</a></code>.</p>

<p>The template path is also configured. And there is a example template located in
<code>myproject/templates/index.html</code>. Yup, it is the initial Django&rsquo;s template, slightly modified.</p>

<h3>Limitations and workarounds</h3>

<p>Not everything is a sea of roses, though:</p>

<ul>
<li>Django does not offer a way to change the project folder name. For that reason, I&rsquo;ve been forced to add a custom code
in manage.py in order to change this folder name to match the application name.</li>
<li>There is some extra code in urls.py too.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Final words</h3>

<p>I hope this can solve some problems for newcomers willing to learn Django. Please <a href="http://herberthamaral.github.io/contact.html">contact me</a>
if you find a bug or if you have a suggestion.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
